talk right now,
and I'll let you all introduce yourselves.
Go for it. Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you Lyle.
Okay. I will read in English.
Please be patient.
Okay.
You have the title of my talk there.
It's quite long.
You can read it.
So in the context of this panel
theme, my presentation
focuses on a specific problem
that I think emerges many times
when artists theories and critiques
explore co-creation with machines.
Bringing post humanism on the table.
Digital techno experimentalism
finds usually affinity with post-human
ism, and I think this is absolutely valid.
But while doing so,
it also encounters difficulties
in navigating the more standardized parts
of collaborative human machine creation
frame within the digital device,
which entails living conditions
formatted, among others, by platform
capitalism,
techno surveillance society,
data extractive, and data colonialism.
Given that elit arts have a quite
long history of co-creation with machines,
it is not surprising at all
that writers, poets and artists
have begun to rapidly experiment
with AI devices.
And clearly
before the great hype around 2022,
when ChatGPT entered the homes
of millions of people who were previously
a bit unaware that they have been
co-existence with the AA since while ago.
I think that I think of the ChatGPT
episode as a turning point,
only because it marks the moment
when AA enters
the collective social imagination
in a way that is both resounding
and concrete in terms
of the practical applications
it enables the church.
This episode indicated
not really a technological,
but a turn, but a social one.
I suggest we could speak of an era defined
not simply by AA,
but by an AA word in which
the mode of presentation of the world
is determined by computability,
produced by machines
created by human beings,
which have become, though
entrenched in the social imagination,
as potentially autonomous.
Autonomous humanity has created machines
capable of constructing
a form of cognition
that in turn defines itself
as the only form of cognition,
and therefore of intelligence
and fantasies
of an artificial superintelligence.
Do not go beyond this
because they do not consider possible
techno diversities, which, according
to you, who are the only guarantee
of know diversity,
the diversity of knowledge systems,
epistemologies
and forms of social organization.
Of course, it's not a matter of reserving
what is known computable for humanity
and what is completely computable
for machines,
because what changes in this leap
from one year to the next
is the possibility of continuing
to uphold the human nonhuman dualism,
which asks for a discussion of post-human
ism and the ways
in which this new era connects
to new conceptions
of the living in the interaction
between humanity, animals, and machines.
The perspective we owe
to the very beginnings of cybernetic.
So the problem when dealing
with the affinity between post-human ism
and AI developments,
is that, on the one hand,
is that on the one hand,
while non-critical experimental
experimentalism without any self
reflexivity also finds
a sphere of affinity with both humanism
based on its challenge to the dominance
implied in the dualism of nature, culture
or humanity machine,
which in the arts go hand in hand
with the modern category of authorship
unique and regional.
On the other hand, its full adherence
to a conception of AA as a post-human
entity falls into the paradox
of obscuring its anchoring in an age
digital device
that gives rise to new ways of domination.
Maybe the type of critical experimentalism
I will discuss here
can partially overcome this paradox.
On top of that,
the discourse of corporations that develop
AA AA points to the ideal
of a complete
blurring of the distinction between
humans and machines,
which would allow us to to inhabit
a world of total democratization
of content, creation and authorship.
The problem is not the spirit
of becoming all artists
and all the aspirations
of the so-called historical avant garde,
but rather that in a anthropocentric
world guided by the major components
of economic power that develop AA,
the initiative position is shaped
by that very power
which, as the radical
AI network points out, causes that.
I quote people of color black,
indigenous, women, queer, transgender,
non-conforming, poor, disabled are
and other communities are pushed to the
to the margins
while consolidating an AA
that is often extractive,
exploitative, surveilled, controlling,
prescriptive and reductionist.
Hence, the problem of equating co-creation
with AA
and post-human ism without further
consideration and aligning it
with the non-critical experimentalism
that views technology as neutral.
My proposal regarding digital techno
poetics, committed
to critical experimentalism, by contrast,
is linked to the possibility
of experimenting through the arts
with openings for situated events
and from a non instrumental dimension.
Even if we work alongside AA,
this would align,
at least in part, with Yuki's suggestion
that rather than creator
creating new media art using AA,
the ideal approach
would be to intervene in AA through art.
With this in
mind, I will explore
two examples of generative
art created in Latin America,
whether with or without AA.
First, one of the blocks created
by Celie that post text
automatically and generally using
combinatorial algorithms algorithms
highlighting
the debate over authorship we have here.
Here it is.
Okay, I have to read this.
The name of the work is eight square
bracket.
Cui k who said he said cool
Q so eight eight square
bracket q to LP backlash, Asterix, DF
and so on.
That's the name of the of the work.
It has a subtitle.
Subtitle which is a blog written
by a machine in its own language,
and the second one, the second work
will be the project entitled
Archival Repression,
created in 2020 by Mercers in Venice.
Oviedo, an artist born in Cuba
and based in Argentina,
a Mexican, but everyone knows him here.
I, I imagine so
a the square bracket, Q2 etc.
presents itself as a machine blow
machines blog and uses a short
combinatorial program
whose output is always illegible
from a human semantic perspective
and is of little or no or no
practical use as data to be incorporated
into the contemporary digital ecosystem.
Since each post appears as a random
string of Ascii signboards symbols,
the piece runs periodically and
automatically from the artist's server,
and although it speaks the language
of the machine, it does not enable
syntactic and semantic operations
with efficient results.
This gives rise to an artistic gesture
that unfolds along at least two lines.
One of them, it summons the block
General January itself
as part of the literary genres
of the self of the human self.
By transferring intimacy to the machine
with a large dose of irony
regarding the general
and the culture of intimacy as spectacle.
The second strand highlights algorithmic
construction within the framework
of framework of a literary conceptualism
that reveals what usually goes unnoticed
in our constant interactions
with digital devices, namely,
the artifice upon
which all online interactions depends.
Along the same lines, a distance
perspective distanced perspective
is established, rather ironic regarding
both human and machine authorship.
This serves both as a
as a critique of dualities and of the
hidden identification of machine
writing as an ideal
post-human post-human entity.
H is square.
I don't know, blah blah blah.
That's not enabled.
And discoveries of meaning.
As other digital combinatorial pieces
usually do,
since nothing is publishes, it's legible.
At most IT discoveries would fall
within the realm of asymmetry poetry.
This only serves to reinforce its place
within critical experiment.
Poetic genealogy genealogies.
On the other hand, archival repression
works with an AI
software in relation
to the use of archiving a relevant issue.
Given that the internet
and social media constitute a vast archive
that is constantly being turned into data
and expropriated for the training
of artificial neural networks.
Beyond the extraction of personal data,
the use of data for training
AI training is part of a presentation
of the word conceived as a total, neutral,
transparent and infallible data set based
on tagging and classification,
and with this it reduces the world
to a unified
and supposedly seamless presentation.
It's not that this happens
only with the data sets
of which machine learning
is based in this.
In this respect, a data set resembles
any other archive
which collects material and classifies
it according to some value
driven system of organization.
However,
when A extracts data from the internet
and social media, it
operates on the basis of what was already
the ideal of data ideology
of the big tech corporations that shape
the internet, social media
and AA, the dream of a total archive
that would organize
all the words information.
That's the
the motto of of of Google Books.
So at civil repression uses
as its data set images that document
institutional repression in the global
South, obtained from the internet
and social media, and processes them
using adversarial
generative neural networks,
trying to recognize human faces
and bodies.
In the process, the AI both recognized
and distorted the source images.
On the one
hand, it recognizes human bodies as such,
but it fails to distinguish which ones
were acting as repressors
and which as the repressed.
On the other hand,
the artificially generated images
frequently feature enveloping,
distorting smoke, as in this image
which obscured the images,
rendering the bodies unrecognizable.
The artist has argued that the distorting
smoke in the generated images function
as a black box
parallel to the algorithmic black box,
in that it produces a quote,
a bias effect on the initial situation
of denunciation or testimony.
Given
that images of institutional repression
uploaded on the to the internet
or social media
are made available to denounce
this illegal exercise of power.
The problem arises
that the very act of creating these online
archives is coopted and colonized,
insofar as they become inputs for AA
as an artistic
project, and tribal repression brings
this issue to light
and at the same time produces images
that cannot be turned into data,
since they are strange enough to throw off
any subsequent training
of artificial neural networks, in a sense,
and artistic disruption occurs.
Isn't it time to flood the internet
and social media
with a tide of distortions of this kind?
The proposal, of course, has imitations
in a sense, and artistic disruption. No.
So I was saying that
it has some limitations, given that
all the images already uploaded
and stored in the past provide sufficient
material for any future machine learning,
I think, and given that we need
undistorted images
in our practical glides.
All in all, what this artistic proposal
would give AA is an understanding
of its own interpretative limitations
regarding the world.
To conclude, I return to the idea
of providing aa other ways of seeing.
I understand that on a general level
in relation to how research
leading to the development of
AA is conducted,
the issue would involve strengthening
the voices of artists
in society
to exert some degree of influence
on the techno scientific
thinking that drives this development.
But if we move to a more specific level,
we find the tension
between the constant colonization
by the digital apparatus
and the critical experimentalism
that seeks to work against the apparatus.
On the one hand, these projects
use algorithms and AA to produce
a new form of media art, as he notes
that in doing so,
they would not go beyond experimentation
that treats AA as a resource,
and as it is given,
it is a given with its orientations,
biases, and conceptual framework.
However, on the other hand, in several
on the
of the artistic procedures
involved in this project projects,
we can see path toward the creative
production of another form of AA.
These are paths and paths
and explorations, each
heading in a different direction.
One of these is linked to self reflexivity
regarding generative algorithms
and AI as a tool,
both using them and distancing from them
by making
the materiality, mechanisms
and underlying concepts visible.
For example on the cells
machines generated blog.
This is reflected in the subtitle A blog
written by a machine in its own language.
Similarly,
on the new version of the cells website,
the code tag provides access to,
among other
pieces, a square, okay brackets, etc.,
as well as to the code
written for this work which was here.
Another such endeavor
aimed at creative production
within an algorithmic real,
including AA, is one that,
to a certain extent disrupts
the colonization of data
by generating test text and images
that are strange and unproductive enough
to hinder the extraction.
This is the case
both with the silicon semi text
and with the images
obliterated by the envelope
enveloping smoke in Inverness
of the archival repression.
One might argue, argue
that these interruptions introduce
other meanings, not so much as the glitch
and healthy nations that are common.
Common side effects of contemporary AA,
but rather
as deliberately sought
after politics of error.
Finally, in the two cases,
there is an interweaving of human
and machine authorship
that allows them to be integrated
into post-human perspectives.
At the same time, however,
there is sufficient estrangement to avoid
becoming tied to uncritical notions
that simply because they are considered
post-human, ist see themselves
as banners of a liberating,
transformative transformation.
On the contrary, the procedure procedures
analyze, facilitate, facilitate
a debate about the contemporary Germany
digital apparatus
which with which they necessarily engage
and which they seek,
at the very least, to disrupt.
We know that the arts do not the world
directly or instantly.
The potential for intervention
based on conceptual
conceptions
is mediated and unfolds over time.
Perhaps no change
will be seen in the future, but rather
the path already opened by this year
era will be sealed into our consciousness.
In that case,
maybe a valid techno poetic option
would be withdrawal
to refuse to play alone.
In another scenario,
if the option of withdrawal
does not convince many people
who produce an experience or experience
contemporary Iliad and arts, it is
because we continue to have this planet
and to interact with the world
at every turn in our daily lives.
Poetically and critically,
inhabiting the world through strength
and the rebellion of the senses,
I think, must be an option.
Thank you very much.
Muchas gracias.
Claudia. Gracias.
Sorry about my
I don't know,
I read in English with many, many breaks.
You know, I have to cut to go.
And you're working in a
in a second language.
I think it's fantastic. Yeah.
Second language
that I've never lived in a country
in an English spoken country,
so it's difficult to reach.
I could not do what you've done.
And I couldn't do it in Spanish, so.
Okay, well. Thank you. Okay.
All right. Thank you.
Veronica.
Are you.
Yes. Over to you.
Take it away.
This is.
Oh, yeah.
You can see it, right?
And then I will.
I know, sorry. It's in process.
It's like.
Sorry.
No, I'm sharing something
that I don't have to share
because I'm putting
the presentation here.
No. Used to do this with my students,
and now I'm.
Yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah, you can see it, right?
Yes. Yeah, yeah.
Now we can see it. Okay.
So thank you for being here.
So nice to see some people like that.
Like Alex, etc..
So. Hello, everybody.
And thanks for being here in this panel.
I've been working
in the last.
In the last two years in Berlin
and in the university
in Australia, Universitet.
And now I've finished my project
and I'm starting
to think new, new exploration
for my research.
So I will explore with you
something I started thinking
and I will be brief,
so don't worry about it.
And the title of our panel
involves also Krona Poetics.
So I would try to.
Yeah, to bring my presentation
to this krona
poetics and experimentation in elit.
The title is, as you can see
in the presentation, slowness as an elite
strategy in the age of hyper acceleration.
And I will talk about this piece of work,
which is local.
So I will read and then we can see
a little bit of the video,
which is the work itself.
And, and I also wanted to say
that I was part of
coeditor of the second volume
of little anthologies,
and this piece of work
is one of the, of the, of the works
that are part of it.
So I invite everybody to,
to also explore the second volume of
and then followed.
Since the beginning
of 21st century, we face a radicalization
of the acceleration process
that was built and consolidated
throughout the century.
In particular,
the 70s and 80s saw the closure of code
and the commodification
of software actions that could have
gradual consequences in terms
of the acceleration of information
distribution,
and with it the difficulty of decoding
and the lack of transparency.
Faced with the proliferation of Opac,
spatial origins and frenetic
temporal alteration,
it appears in multiplication
of layers of information
from which we know only a tiny part of it.
It's a generative architecture.
But while the foundation
of the Great Acceleration
were being led during the 20th century,
the condition of production
were sustained in a society
still dominated
but by an ideal of linear progress
where the work could still be observed
from modern coordinates.
However, nowadays
we live under the primacy of acceleration
and the explosion of a linear or in some.
In consequence, it becomes possible
to fulfill an algorithmic society
which, as Martin
Endler and Malcolm Allamakee argue,
is currently an infrastructural condition
that defined, that defines us
even though it functionalities
based on increasing opacity,
we are faced with a phenomenon
based on two characteristics
the opacity of the language of algorithm
code,
and the ratification
of constant data flows.
That implies a high degree
of incomprehension on the part of humans.
In both cases,
speed will play a fundamental role
in the exercise of this power
over over life,
giving that its magnitude
and radiation are beyond our control
due to its scale and impact.
So, returning to the initial postulate,
I will propose to reflect
on some procedure procedural strategies
that slow down
temporal temporal spatial modulation
facing the colonization of the device
in today's algorithmic society.
In particular,
I will talk about, as I said, local,
a piece that plays with the speed
in the opposite direction
to the current, accelerate flow
of infinite recommendations locally.
And there is a piece by Martin Rangel
and consists of a series
of visual poem poems in motion or,
as the authors
call them, farewell sculptures,
which explore subjects
such as disappearance
and the constitution of reality.
I can this is a video
hosted in YouTube,
so I just will show you.
I don't know.
I am I.
Yes. Okay, so I
will just play just a little bit.
It's very loud, but as you can
so you can see it.
It's a video hosted in YouTube.
That piece itself, it's not a video
make with the piece.
So I just wanted to show
you just some seconds. And.
In this consensus.
And so for those who
who can listen in can't sorry.
Listen in Spanish and read this.
What it's saying is not the same
the boys.
It's the recording recording something
different than what it is written here.
Like I wasn't silhouette, etc.
it's hard to read and to hear at
the same time, but it's just that, right?
It's a, it's a, it's culture emotion
as the author defined it.
And so and the author had created.
For the sound, as I said,
along with the electronic music
produced specifically for this piece,
a robotic voice
read a text generated by AI using ChatGPT,
and the instructions are now in the
in the presentation.
And for generating this text
where right and
explain object oriented and ontology,
the principle of quantum nonlocality
and by way of conclusion establish
a relationship between the two concepts.
So the piece is an exercise that combines
visual poetry,
emotion, philosophy,
quantum physics in the sense
thematic, thematically music,
AI, and computer inside voice.
The call is then poetically activated
in this video, created,
as you could see in green and black, it
features moving images
that form geometric figures made of words.
This links this linked to visual poetry
and particularly of the present of
of the precepts of Brazilian concrete.
In this sense, the process of slowing down
has to do with the interplay between
opacity and transparency in the laborious
and sometimes even impossible
reading of these various cultures.
As we we could see is even if,
you know Spanish, it's very hard to read
and it doesn't have the objective
to be written right.
As it is a video, it contains
no external interaction or variation.
The text are brief,
although difficult to read.
However, after pausing to look,
we are able to decode somehow
touch the shadow of of a sombra della
once again the work it has I caught.
Once again,
the work appeals to contemplation
as a way of slowing down perception
and delta.
Martin.
The repetitive and statistical procedure
of the algorithm,
which is based on the impossibility
of understanding
grid given the speed
at which we are exposed to it,
I will.
I have a quote where I think
I don't have much time, so I go further.
Further.
In this piece we read, we could read
sometimes when when we are able
to read borders that come together
without touching and of course
locality proposes.
So already in this in its time a new
spatial modulation that implies within.
But at the same time,
because it is a repetitive spirit,
it allows for another temporal modulation
associated with the cyclical
rather than the linearity inherent
in the idea of progress
and the calculable, calculable,
or isn't of modernity.
And part of this hyper acceleration.
Right.
So this appropriation of time and space
allows us to question
that only the characteristic
of the increasingly impossible
to read programing coding of algorithm
society, but also opens stop
or isn't a future possibilities
in the sense
defined by Franco variety.
So to conclude this linearity
proceed procedure in locality
stunted work
with the slowness to make explicit
any any impact of
the leap of a scale
in which we are in March now.
Thank you.
I tried to practice
I a nickel.
It's so hard to say,
but we are aware all this in language,
with the language that is not our
wonderful job and wonderful piece.
Thank you very much.
Excellent. Okay.
Are you ready to.
Yes. Queued up.
All right.
Take it away.
Yeah. Hello, everybody.
Thank you for being here
and and for your interest in this panel.
And my name is German and I am German.
I live in Chile for 20 years now,
and my research fields are asked
to media arts, digital arts.
That's why we came together with Claudia
and Veronica in some occasions.
And this panel was bigger,
as we said in the beginning.
But now we are three and I think
we had a lot of time
and now we don't have so much time.
That's always
what what what what happens.
So I'm in a kind of skeptical moment right
now, observing
what's going on in the world
and especially in Latin America.
I have some remarks
and then I will talk about
two projects artistic projects
from Latin American artists.
My talk is
is there
techno capitalism, techno poetics? And
there's a
certain
urgency to rethinking artistic production.
In the area of AI,
it is important to imagine and build
new forms of connection and collaboration
between human beings and machines.
At a time
when the distribution of the sensible is
a far more severe issue than it was
30 years ago.
When Jacques wrote
about the interplay of esthetics
and politics
in the making of emancipated communities.
Generative AI is transforming life
forms and cultures of knowledge and stands
as one of the major engines of techno
capitalism, a phenomenon with many faces
cognitive capitalism, surveillance
capitalism, platform capitalism and so on.
What is at stake here?
It's difficult to think about innovative
artistic forms and operations
without reckoning
with a new reactionary threat.
What, when and how is art
when democracy is no longer worth
defending?
For those who dominate political discourse
and technological development?
When the most powerful corporations
producing AI technologies are reshaping
political systems themselves,
seeing a new forms of monarchy
a way out of the poly crisis
we are living through blaming democracy
for every evil,
calling it an endeavor of the Antichrist.
The most prominent representative,
as you know, of techno capitalism
today is Peter Thiel,
who recently bought a mansion in Buenos
Aires, near one of the most
devoted photos
of his anti-democratic vision
Javier Miley, in some sense
cosplay copy of Trump,
the original superhero is well on his way
to demolishing the institutions
that safeguard civil society, embodying
the breakdown of politics itself.
Recent election results
in other Latin American countries
such as Chile, Peru and Colombia, point
at the same direction.
Those who govern the world
today are not politicians, but CEOs,
together with lawyers who practice
whose practices
are far more damaging than anything
so good man ever managed.
In Better Call Saul,
Sam Altman, Elon Musk and many others
represented the reactionary dark
enlightenment, a concept coined
by the influential blogger
Curtis Yavin around 2007 and later
elaborated by British philosopher
Nick land between 2 and 8 and 2000.
12. Reading lens blog post.
Today is chilling,
they read, as a prefiguring of
what is happening right now
across much of the world, all the more
so if we if we recall lens beginnings
at Warwick
alongside cyber feminist
Sally plant and left thinker Mark Fisher.
So coming
back to our central question,
how can we imagine and build
new forms of connection, collaboration
between human beings
and machines under these circumstances?
How our technological and unnatural
experiment, experimentation possible?
To what extent could techno diversity
and cosmo techniques, as you puts it?
And Claudia also cited him a lot produce,
produce, counter
reactions and redistribute the sensible
between humans and machines.
Between humans and machines
lie latent spaces
that generate apathetic interactions.
There's something I develop in my
and my book that I have.
I hadn't commented,
I haven't commented it.
It's a new book that I published
like half a half a year ago,
and that is the tendency
to perceive connections, patterns,
or messages in random data
to let an American artist
productively engage
this this phenomenon in work.
I'd like to comment on briefly.
The first one is is the one you see,
and I invite you to go to this web page.
It's a very complex
and and detailed work.
Diagnose from 2024.
Diego Bonilla is the artisan programmer.
It's a very complex
and spectral generative archive,
an unsettling artifice
that opens a space of survival
for violated women
in a second artificial life,
where materials connect and flow
among themselves.
Requiem Jonas generates works
that show in prolonged
the past the passage from life to death,
assembling bodies
with bodies, materials with materials,
crossing the animates with the inanimate.
The effective gestures of women
with texts, books, cars,
tapes, cables, flags,
shoes, instruments, tools,
symbols, words, images and objects
in unusual combinations.
You see some examples right now.
This is the bigger,
the bigger focus and the small.
The detailed focus
of what you see in these images.
And you read some poems
there on the left and,
and the explication about how
the artist construct the portrays.
And so what do we see here?
What do the spectral mechanic modern human
portrays convey?
Femicides occur daily in cities
and towns across the Americas,
Europe and Africa.
There are periodic news reports they go,
and not unnoticed, almost immediately
becoming
the new eerie normal.
Bonilla interacts with the non-conscious
cognition of his machine there.
This is a concept developed by Katherine
Hayles, and together they generate
haunting poems in pathways of women
murdered in 25 countries around the world.
In 2024.
The machine converts
these horrifying facts into algorithmic
poems that cross the screen
in a back and forth movement.
In this spectral poses,
each of the roughly
20,000 portrays is a true tribute
to a woman
who lost her life
to an excess of male violence.
At the same time,
it's a striking number of the creations
repeat an idealization of the female body,
a biased pattern
of a certain type of beauty
replicated by the machine.
Also very weird.
Among the posters,
multiple connections unfold.
We see fighting women, cyborg women, women
composed of biological
and artificial materials
surrounded by objects of every kind,
accompanied by the poems that honor them.
Each work is dense with detail,
attributes, everyday
objects, rare and curious things.
It is a digital wonder camera, a cabinet
of curiosities of extraordinary,
extraordinary scale,
born of an artificial imagination
shared between human being and machine.
We see incomplete, deformed, deceased,
assembled, dissected
faces and bodies staged in singular
and astonishing assemblages,
standing out against the sea of data
and images in which we all swim every day.
Unachievable in extent.
Philippe Rivas.
I'm citing The Artist,
a series of photographic looking images
representing homosexual couples, queer
and non-binary working class people from
the early 20th century in Latin America.
The images were created using generative
artificial intelligence models
that process databases
so neither the photographic images
nor the people depicted in them
ever actually existed.
That's
what Philippe Rivas writes in his book.
He brings together 180 images
simulating photographs of a past
that never existed.
Quasi photographs, as Rivas calls them.
This is a queer counter archive that set
against the scant
existing archives of homosexuals
who were declared degenerates at the time
and remained
so classified until the 60s.
It is a political counter archive
that stages a reality that was hidden,
unrecorded or unmediated, and therefore
officially nonexistent, eluding
the mean average images, as he calls
them, generated by most AI models.
This project activates
a degenerative power within the complex
recursive processing of the algorithms,
producing startling
images that turn their own errors
into evidence of the archives.
Paradoxical in existence,
existence, and Enix's.
It is a queer process
of a process of producing queer images,
an exercise in ApoE4
that begins from the distortions
and deformations inherent
to recursive machine learning systems.
What do we see in these 180 images?
We're in homosexual working class couples.
Yeah. More examples
in Latin America
in diverse poses and circumstances.
Embracing, kissing, holding hands.
The interlacing of hands
is a recurring striking motif,
the punctum of many images.
That at least is the first impression.
But we also see embedded
in the images reproduce
with great quality in the book.
The operating systems of the eye models
in its imperfection, errors
that don't match human
perception of the world are
the deformation of bodies,
especially hands and faces
marks another layer of more than human
perception, turning
what is seen into specters,
not photographic specters, but mocenigo
synthetic algorithmic ones.
Analog
photography and film have always moved on
a spectral frequency
between presence and absence.
Life and death.
As Roland Bard and Jacques
Derrida developed in their texts.
Here, however,
we encounter spectral and apathetic poets
between human being and machine.
For Rivas, the errors constitute
an additional layer of bodily dissidents,
guaranteeing the radical evidence
that these images could not have been.
But they are here.
They are in their apathetic forms, drawn
from the latent space of the machines
artificial neural networks.
They call on us to see and read.
Read them in multiple ways,
carrying contemplation
into an exercise
of complementary perception
coming to the
end, one more element of this project
deserves attention
its passage into the object book.
Taking the images out of the digital
environment is a significant gesture,
one selected from the latent space
and fixed in a folder on the computer.
These images head out on the path
to the printing press, materializing
differently, becoming physical, settling,
settling into an interface.
In this new material.
Materiality
between the digital and the analog.
What stands out is a simulation
of period photography photographs
the grain that stains the yellow
yellowish tint.
As you see here in this example.
Another dimension.
Do these quasi photographs
from a photo album.
What do they remember?
The future past of past?
Future rather a past, rather past futures.
Another creature of the fourth memory,
as the Canadian French artist
Gregory calls a synthetic creation
of artificial imagination, this time
born of a political vindicating gesture
with material insistence.
Thank you very much.
Thank you all
so much for these fascinating talks.
We do have about 12 minutes
for discussion, questions,
comments, feedback
and feel free to converse in
whatever language
the question is asked of you, I suppose.
Yeah,
so everyone can feel free
that you can raise your hand.
You can post questions in the chat
and you can.
Wave madly at me like a car blow up
car dancing man.
And or you can just unmute yourself
and ask a question.
Anything anyone wants to throw out there.
If anybody is anybody there
who wants to talk.
Because I just have a very quick question
for Claudia,
but I can ask why was later.
Now I'm wondering if the silly in the
in the piece of work of this
deal understanding he produced with AI
because I understand that he he's no,
no because.
Yes. No, no. Yes.
He he wrote the algorithm
and now this is previous
he began with this in 2008,
but it's still running and the.
Yeah. No it's not. He never included.
That's what I mean like in the terms in in
almost 20 years he never used it for it.
He never changed the way to produce it.
No no no he never changed that. No.
And you know,
when I in the final part of my talk,
I said something about withdrawal.
It was really because he has decided
to stop producing
digital art and literature.
Two years ago he in
2024, he said, okay, it's it's enough.
I think I published a long conversation
with him
in Spanish in Journal in Argentina.
I can send you here by the chat,
the, the,
the address and the we discuss
a lot about okay, what's the stake here?
Are we stopping creating?
I was thinking, but every day EA
is everywhere. And
okay he is very skeptical now like valve
and said he's now a bit more skeptical
than maybe two years ago.
And that happened to you too.
So no, I know, I know him
and I talked to him about it.
So that's why he wrote the algorithm
and he still has this ironic
perspective,
you know, the message saying something.
But we can understand that,
Maybe it was.
Can you
explain a bit more about apathetic,
the apathetic perspective? How?
I don't know, I think that I googled that.
I try to to understand what it is,
but in the case of the
the project by Philippe Rivas,
it's like he puts together
things that never existed, existed.
So, okay.
Is it an apathetic.
I'm not sure.
Maybe it is
because you know more about that than me.
No, no.
Well, next month I will go to
Buenos Aires and I will be okay.
One book.
The book? Yeah. The book. Okay.
Thank you, I will, I will know I
this project by Philippe Rivas.
It's very well
known here in Argentina even.
Yeah.
People who is not really working
on the digital art
or the electronic literature,
it has become something that.
Okay.
I mean, he's, he's
working with with a friend James Martin
this the studio somebody and
they are developing figures
projects with, with AI
and the the interesting gesture here
or operation
I think is bringing it to to to publish
to publish a book out of that
very high quality book.
I mean, the images are very, very
done with, with a, with a high quality.
And what I think is
we are always looking for patterns, right.
That's a survival.
Pattern.
I mean, we, we,
we need patterns to survive.
That's what I want to say.
And that's something we are.
We are.
Translating to to the machines
and our interactions
with machines in different languages.
We are not we are not understanding
what the machine is doing,
you know, so this this is always
an apathetic interaction finally.
And what, what what I think
what Felipe Arribas is doing is
doing
productively, you know,
to take the structures of perception
and do it productively in his,
in his book or in his project
because he he also, of course,
generates images and texts
in the digital space. Yes.
But it's so interesting
to, to to just to publish it,
to come out of this digital space
and what, what occurs there.
Because there you can touch the book,
you have the book in your hands, you know,
and this is very different.
The perception is very different.
And I think all about
AI has has to do with perception.
A book I'm falling a lot
is selling the perception machine.
You know, I think there's
a lot of structure also there.
Although,
she doesn't name it like this, you know.
Yeah, yeah.
And it was interesting that in the book,
as you say, there are details
that we passed like we don't see in
on screen details disturbed.
I don't know the details or is real
or something like that.
Yeah.
I think there are some in the chat.
Yeah. Yes. Yes.
So like asks
I'd love to hear your thoughts
on resistance to AI or technology
more generally.
Your talks all touch on some form of that.
Sorry, the chat shifted,
your talks all touch on some form of that,
none of which entails a refusal to AI.
Can we really critique AI without AI?
I think we are not speaking about refusal
because we all live in this world world
era, but not taking
for granted and
not taking it, not going with the flow,
you know, because I think that the most
interesting artistic projects
that are dealing with AA,
they are doing something
that it's not quite
the usual things because AA is
used by many people today, every day, by
for so many tasks, you know, and the
it's usually used without any
kind of reflexivity
or something like that, like a tool.
It's given like a tool,
but it entails a lot as all technology.
I know, I know that,
but now we are in this turning point
where when AA it's like everywhere
and we at ELO
are speaking about EA and.
And artists are always trying
to think about that.
I'm not thinking really about refusal,
but because we are dealing with it
every day.
But yes, trying to think
some past of,
I don't know, some gestures, arts.
Finally, it's all about gestures
because, you know,
we don't go to the streets
now and change the world
because we are saying this.
But anyway, I think it's better to say
this than not something like that.
But maybe Volf and Veronica has something
to say about that
later.
I totally agree.
I think that the only thing that
I don't know if the only thing,
but something that can can be done
is to resist through it, with it.
And also like observing
that is very important to observe
which concept.
It's the main concept of AI,
which is, yeah, this hyper production
or as Claudia said,
resolves so so, so so many tasks.
And then as I was proposing,
okay, how can we work with slowness,
which is okay to slow down
this hyper acceleration?
We all live and we all are
immersed in using it without decoding.
And so how
this can be any strategy of art,
but the artists will need to study
and to be in, in this hyper acceleration
to reflect
if he wants or if she wants to do it.
So I think the strategies are more
that strategies or gestures
to show the opposite or this.
This can be a resistance.
It's always within the AI.
Yeah, maybe one sentence more.
I think the problem is is not AI.
Of course it's the capture of AI
by techno capitalism.
That's what I think.
So what can we do about that? And
it's impossible
to to act
without AI, to think without AI nowadays.
And what Elisha points out
in her question.
Yeah, it's a kind of kind
of nostalgic perception with the arrows.
His Philippe is really interested
in this,
these queer things, you know,
queer and error things and distortions.
And I think this is one, one, one
possibility to observe
from the arts, from the digital arts,
from, from every, from the visual arts.
Also, what is really happening right now?
What is the problem?
I think the main problem is
the capture of AI.
And with that,
the capture of imagination between,
you know, the interplay
between generation and image.
I think this is the main problem
and projects
we are talking about right now,
we were talking about today,
are all projects who put this
in the center of of reflection,
you know,
how is imagination functioning right now?
And not only generation of images
of texts, because this is a loss
of imagination, I think.
I think we need we.
Was there a question?
I don't know, it's kind of moderating.
Sorry. No, no, it's all right.
It's already time to go.
Yeah, it is time so quickly once we are.
Yeah. Hi.
Hello. Thanks a lot. Claudia. Veronica.
And for this presentations,
we're very interesting.
Very magnificent.
Especially because those bring
this kind of topic, you know, to the table
in the Latin American context
that, as you mentioned,
and I think it's very important
at this stage
in different politics or geopolitics,
I think most of the geopolitics
that are happening right now, it is
happening because of
this turning point, as mentioned, Claudia,
in climate change,
but also in the technological change.
And it is neat as well
to have like some sort of
political and ethical position
and something that I admired,
for instance, about the selling,
you know, that he really stands in.
I'm not going there. I mean,
he respects the people that he goes there.
But he said.
For me, it is done.
I am working on myself
and that is good as well.
You know, it's
it's like I think it's also a way to say
how much is enough for somebody
for as a question for itself, right?
For himself. Sorry.
And in the case of Bonilla
that I also work
with Bonilla here at Nam and with Rodolfo,
I saw how he had been developing
this piece.
Fantastic pieces,
especially as you mentioned.
It is like a very how you said complex,
like there are many, many points
as a system.
You know, it's much more like a system
art of peace, you know, because basically
it is running every day
or every two weeks or something like that,
and creating those poems,
recollecting the news,
scrapping the news from the internet.
So yeah, and I have seen also
how he's changing his position
about AI and the use of AI in the US.
In the universities, for instance.
You know how the machinery is pushing,
you know, to use AI or some sort
of AI inside of the university,
what it has,
what means AI in terms of.
Surveillance, right.
The case of,
for instance, of OpenAI and and unclothed,
which became itself a topic.
So sorry to interrupt. Totally. Yes.
We have to wrap up.
So sorry
I waited for all of you
to to the workshop.
We need we need to have writers.
Writers, right? Yeah.
We cannot even cord
follow the conversation elsewhere.
Yeah. Okay. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Yes.
Thank you all so much.
Excellent panel. Apologies for the cutoff.
No. Don't worry.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody
much for our next panel on Eliza.
Yes. Please do join us.